<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://nathan-mccallum.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://nathan-mccallum.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2020-04-10T23:05:45+10:00</updated><id>http://nathan-mccallum.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nathan’s Public Domicile</title><subtitle>Hi! I'm a web developer who specializes in Ruby, Rails, Node.js &amp; frontend technologies such as React. In my spare time I like to play guitar and experiment with electronic music production.</subtitle><author><name>Nathan McCallum</name><email>nathan@1vas.me</email></author><entry><title type="html">Album Review: Le Noise by Neil Young</title><link href="http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/10/album-review-le-noise-by-neil-young.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Album Review: Le Noise by Neil Young" /><published>2020-04-10T12:52:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-04-10T12:52:00+10:00</updated><id>http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/10/album-review-le-noise-by-neil-young</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/10/album-review-le-noise-by-neil-young.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been reading &lt;em&gt;Waging Heavy Pace&lt;/em&gt; (Neil Young’s autobiography) and a natural part of such a process is to listen to the music that’s mentioned along the way.&lt;!--more--&gt;
I’d already heard a lot of the classics so we don’t need to go there, but &lt;em&gt;Le Noise&lt;/em&gt; got my attention because it’s pretty different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instrumentation for the whole album is deceptively simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil’s voice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acoustic guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A handful of synthesizers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Black&quot;&gt;Old Black&lt;/a&gt;’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite tracks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-walk-with-me&quot;&gt;1. Walk With Me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Walk With Me&lt;/em&gt; opens the album, introducing the distorted guitar sound and heavily delayed vocals that we hear through most of the album.
The song itself is fairly simple, Neil’s vocals sounding as good as ever.
The thing that made the song for me however was the lovely ambient electronic breakdown at the end.
As if to give us a peep into some other world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-love-and-war&quot;&gt;2. Love and War&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth track on the album and we finally get a different texture, acoustic guitar and voice.
On first listening it felt like a long time coming, but well worth it.
The song is a wonderful ballad, mournful but somewhat hopeful.
Admitting a lack of knowledge, despite seeing a lot. Hoping for things to be better, know that they may not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the nice touches with the harmony through the piece.
The verses are in A minor and choruses in G, with some interesting interplay between the two.
Particularity the usage of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;D7&lt;/code&gt; (the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;V&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;G&lt;/code&gt;) resolving to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Am&lt;/code&gt; instead.
Music theorists would call this a deceptive resolution but to me it just feels like we’re going back down into the trenches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-peaceful-valley-boulevard&quot;&gt;3. Peaceful Valley Boulevard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovely, mournful, really nice song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When learning this it took me quite a while to realize what was going on in the chorus.
At first I thought it was an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ebm7b5&lt;/code&gt; and was trying to find a voicing that matched what I was hearing.
In the end I worked out that it was actually an even more dissonant &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ebdim7&lt;/code&gt; chord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the break to F major took me right back to &lt;em&gt;Starman&lt;/em&gt; by David Bowie.
It only goes for 30 seconds but the effect was immense.
And the deceptive resolution (there’s the term again!) back to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Em&lt;/code&gt; felt like it all just died and faded away into memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-didnt-like&quot;&gt;Things I didn’t like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no drums! This is great in the acoustic songs but there were moments in the electric tracks where I just wanted more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, after hearing &lt;em&gt;Walk With Me&lt;/em&gt; I felt like &lt;em&gt;Sign of Love&lt;/em&gt; was a bit plain.
This was followed by &lt;em&gt;Someone’s Gonna Rescue You&lt;/em&gt; and it took me a while to shake the feeling of &lt;em&gt;“Is the whole album like this?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in fact that’s the main gripe I have: except for &lt;em&gt;Walk With Me&lt;/em&gt;, the electric tracks all feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My overall rating:&lt;/strong&gt; 6/10&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan McCallum</name><email>nathan@1vas.me</email></author><category term="album-reviews" /><summary type="html">Recently I’ve been reading Waging Heavy Pace (Neil Young’s autobiography) and a natural part of such a process is to listen to the music that’s mentioned along the way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Started</title><link href="http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/05/getting-started.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Started" /><published>2020-04-05T18:19:00+10:00</published><updated>2020-04-05T18:19:00+10:00</updated><id>http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/05/getting-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://nathan-mccallum.com/2020/04/05/getting-started.html">&lt;p&gt;It is a cool Sunday evening and I am once again experimenting with my personal site.
Over the years I’ve run several different &lt;em&gt;“Hello, World - this is me”&lt;/em&gt;-type sites and nothing has quite stuck.&lt;!--more--&gt;
Given the vast array of options, I’ve never settled on any one thing.
I can at least remember trying Wordpress, Ghost, SquareSpace, as well as various things I’ve hacked together and hosted on GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This current iteration is a Jekyll site hosted for free on GitHub Pages.
And I think it’s going to work.
Why?
Because I changed my expectation.
I realized I was chasing a “perfect” option when instead I just needed to find “my” option.
I’m even using the default Jekyll theme right now.
Because it doesn’t actually matter.
I’ve seen many (more successful) blogs that look worse than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been pondering recently why I am resistant to change.
My thoughts so far have been that when I am presented with a new situation, I see an infinity of possibilities, or none at all.
For instance, I often look at an empty Ableton Live session and feel that I could make any music I want.
But I do nothing because I can’t find &lt;strong&gt;the thing&lt;/strong&gt; (musical, lyrical, emotional, or otherwise) that I’m trying to express.
In 2016 I tried to start a blog, but never wrote a single post because I felt like I had nothing at all to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of a quote from Winston Churchill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To improve is to change; to be perfect is to change often.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there’s a middle ground between the two extremes of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Infinity&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;?
A state where one can keep moving without losing track of what’s important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s too many possibilities, reduce them down until you’re left with one.
If you have no possibilities, do something stupid until something comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of my personal blog, it doesn’t actually really matter whether I use SquareSpace, Ghost, or something I hacked together.
I’ve been enjoying my Rails work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://thegrantshub.com&quot;&gt;The Grants Hub&lt;/a&gt; so I chose a Ruby-based static site generator.
But it could have been anything.
The point was that I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of my music, I’ve found that I can get better results by writing guitar parts instead of getting stuck in the details of synthesizer design, mixing or drum programming.
I can then swap the guitars with other sounds or get other people to play the parts, all of which can potentially serve the music better.
However I wouldn’t have gotten there had I not gone back and reduced the possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now we’re experiencing a pandemic of unprecedented scale.
On social media I’m seeing many posts saying “use the isolation time to learn new skills”.
I don’t buy it though. I feel like I’ve got enough going on with reading, music and work.
But perhaps this is another instance of me seeing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan McCallum</name><email>nathan@1vas.me</email></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html">It is a cool Sunday evening and I am once again experimenting with my personal site. Over the years I’ve run several different “Hello, World - this is me”-type sites and nothing has quite stuck.</summary></entry></feed>